<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4443 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4443.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2827 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2827.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6724 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6724.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5340 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5340.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.arkko-homenet-prefix-assignment SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.arkko-homenet-prefix-assignment.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-ospf-ospfv3-autoconfig SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-ospf-ospfv3-autoconfig.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-homenet-arch SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-homenet-arch.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.baker-ipv6-ospf-dst-src-routing SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.baker-ipv6-ospf-dst-src-routing.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.baker-ipv6-isis-dst-src-routing SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.baker-ipv6-isis-dst-src-routing.xml">
]>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-troan-homenet-sadr-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="SADR">IPv6 Multihoming with Source Address Dependent Routing (SADR)</title>

    <author fullname="Ole Troan" initials="O" surname="Troan">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Philip Pedersens vei 1</street>
          <city>Lysaker</city>
          <code>1366</code>
          <country>Norway</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ot@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials='L' surname="Colitti" fullname='Lorenzo Colitti'>
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Roppongi Hills Mori Tower PO box 22</street>
          <city>Minato</city>
          <region>Tokyo</region>
          <code>106-6126</code>
          <country>Japan</country>
        </postal>
        <email>lorenzo@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2013" />
    <area>Internet</area>
    <workgroup>Homenet working Group</workgroup>

    <!--  SECTION 0:  Abstract                      -->

    <abstract>
      <t>A multihomed network using provider aggregatable addresses
      must send the packet out the right path to avoid violating the
      provider's ingress filtering. This memo suggests a mechanism
      called Source Address Dependent Routing to solve that
      problem.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <!--  SECTION 1:  Introduction                  -->

    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>IPv6 is designed to support multiple addresses on an
      interface, and the intention was to use this feature to support
      multihoming with provider aggregatable addresses.</t>

      <t>One difficulty of multihoming with provider-aggregatable
      space is that providers typically employ <xref
      target="RFC2827">BCP38</xref> filtering. If a network sends
      traffic to its upstream provider using a source address that was
      not assigned by that provider, the traffic will be
      dropped. Thus, if a network is multihomed to multiple providers,
      it must ensure that traffic is sent out the correct exit for the
      packet's source address.</t>

      <t>As long as upstream traffic is sent to the correct provider,
      hosts inside the network are free to use source addresses
      assigned by any of the network's upstream providers. In such a
      scenario, each host has multiple addresses, one or more from
      each provider the network is connected to. The network ensures
      that packets are sent to the correct upstream by forwarding
      packets based on the destination address and the source address.
      This we call source address dependent routing (SADR). This memo
      shows how SADR can be used to implement multihoming.</t>

    </section>

    <!--  SECTION 2: REQUIREMENTS LANGUAGE          -->

    <section anchor="conventions" title="Conventions">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- conventions -->

    <section title="Terminology">

      <t><list hangIndent="24" style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Service Provider">An entity that provides the
          network with external connectivity, e.g. to the Internet.</t>

          <t hangText="WAN Interface">An interface connected to a
          Service Providers. WAN interfaces may either be physical
          links or virtual interfaces such as tunnels. WAN interfaces
          are used to send ingress traffic from the Internet to the
          End-User, and egress traffic from the End-User network to
          the Internet. Ingress traffic may be received on any active
          interface at any time. Egress traffic follows a set of rules
          within the router in order to choose the proper WAN
          interface.</t>

          <t hangText="Border Router">A border router has one or more
          external interfaces connecting it to one or more Service
          Providers. The border router receives one or more delegated
          prefixes, each associated with one or more WAN interfaces.
          </t>

          <t hangText="External Route">A route that is learned from a
          Service Provider. Each External Route has an Acceptable
          Source Prefix which determines which source addresses may use
          that route.</t>

          <t hangText="Internal Router">A router that is not a Border
          Router.</t>

          <t hangText="Internal Route">A route to a destination inside the
          network.</t>

        </list></t>
    </section>

    <!--  SECTION 3: DESCRIPTION                   -->


    <section title="Using SADR for multihoming">
      <t>SADR is similar to policy based routing. This memo
      proposes a simple extension to the destination based longest
      match algorithm to constrain it to source address.</t>

      <t>In order to support ingress filtering by upstream networks,
      the network MUST treat external routes specially. Ingress
      filtering MAY also be used internally, by installing (S,D)
      routes for locally assigned prefixes, where the source prefix
      would be the aggregatable prefix. If no ingress filtering is
      performed inside the network, then normal non-source constrained
      forwarding is used.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="A Conceptual Forwarding Algorithm">
      <t>This section describes a conceptual forwarding algorithm. An
      implementation might implement this differently, e.g. with
      multiple tables, as long as the external behaviour is as
      described.</t>

      <t>First a longest match lookup is done in the routing table for
      the destination address, then for the resulting set a longest
      matching lookup is done for the source address.</t>

      <t>In a destination based routing table, an entry in the routing
      table can be shown as "D -> NH". That is, to get to a
      destination D, use next-hop NH. For a source constrained routing
      table we propose the following notation. (Source Network,
      Destination network) -> Next-hop. (S, D) -> NH. A route that is
      not source constrained can be represented as (*, D) -> NH.</t>

      <t>For convenience this document shows the routing table as a
      single destination based routing table, with source address
      constrained paths. This does not preclude other implementations,
      as long as the external behaviour is the same.</t>

      <t>A router forwarding a packet does a longest match look-up on
      the destination address. If this is a (*, D) entry, it forwards
      the packet out the best next-hop as before (doing equal cost
      multi path load balancing etc). If the look-up results in a (S,
      D) entry, the look-up function does a longest match on the
      source address among the set of (S, D) paths. If there is a
      match the packet is forwarded out the given next-hop, if not an
      ICMP destination address unreachable message, code 5 is returned
      <xref target="RFC4443"/>. A routing entry may have both (S, D)
      paths and (*, D) paths. The longest match wins.</t>

      <t>The following example show the routing table of a network
      connected to two ISPs, ISP A and ISP B. Both ISPs offer default
      connectivity and ISP B also offers a more specific route to a
      walled garden service.</t>

      <figure align="center" anchor="rt" title="Example Routing Table">
        <preamble></preamble>
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[

 (2001:db8::/56, ::/0) -> ISP_A          # Default route to ISP A
 (2001:db9::/56, ::/0) -> ISP_B          # Default route to ISP B
 (*, 2001:db8::/64) -> R1                # Internal network, prefix from A
 (*, 2001:db8:1::/64) -> R2              # Internal network, prefix from A
 (*, 2001:db9::/64) -> R1                # Internal network, prefix from B
 (*, 2001:db9:1::/64) -> R2              # Internal network, prefix from B
 (*, fd00::/64) -> R3                    # Internal network ULA
 (2001:db9::/56, 2001:420::/32) -> ISP_B # Walled garden route from ISP B

        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>A packet with the SA, DA of 2001:db8::1, 2001:dead:beef::1
      would be forwarded to ISP A, likewise a packet with SA, DA
      2001:db9::1, 2001:dead:beef::1 would be forward to ISP B. An
      packet with SA,DA 2001:db8::1, 2001:db9::1 would be forwarded
      using normal destination based routing. A packet to the walled
      garden SA,DA 2001:db9::1, 2001:420::1 would be sent to ISP B. A
      packet with SA,DA 2001:db8::1,2001:420::1 would be dropped with
      an ICMP unreachable message being sent back.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Routing considerations">
      <t>Now that we have described the function of the source
      constrained routing table. How does the table get populated?</t>

      <section title="Routing Protocol extensions">
      <t>The generic answer is that the routing protocol used in the
      network has to be extended to support (S, D)
      routes. Specifically, the routing protocol should distribute,
      for each External Route, the Acceptable Source Prefix(es) for
      that route. This may be done, for example, using <xref
      target="I-D.baker-ipv6-ospf-dst-src-routing"/> or <xref
      target="I-D.baker-ipv6-isis-dst-src-routing"/>. In the case of
      OSPFv3, for example, external routes are advertised in an
      AS-External-prefix LSA, <xref target="RFC5340"/>
      </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Simplified SADR in home networks">
        <t>In a home network using a dynamic prefix assignment mechanism
        such as <xref target="I-D.arkko-homenet-prefix-assignment"/> it
        may be known that a particular Border Router is announcing both
        an External Route and a Usable Prefix (for example, if the
        same router ID is announcing both). In this case, interior routers
        may assume that the Acceptable Source Prefix of the External Route
        announced by that Border Router is in fact the Usable Prefix
        announced by that Border Router.</t>

        <t>An internal router when receiving a AS-External LSA route
        will install that in the routing table as normal. When the
        internal router receives a usable prefix as part of prefix
        assignment, the router shall add source constrained entries to
        all the AS-External routes received from the same border router
        (matching router-ID).</t>

        <t>Routes that are not associated with a border router or are
        not AS-External do not have source constrained paths.</t>

        <t>The routing protocol requirements for simplified SADR in
        the home network are:
        <list style="numbers">
        <t>Routing protocol must flood all information to all routers in
        the home network. (Single area).</t>
        <t>Prefix assignment and unicast routing must be done in the same
        protocol.</t>
        <t>A router must be uniquely identified (router-id) so that
        router advertisements and prefix assignment can be tied
        together</t>
        </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Interaction between routers and hosts">
      <t>Generally, hosts need not be aware that SADR is in use in the
      network. Hosts simply choose source addresses and the network
      will deliver the traffic to the appropriate upstream.

      One exception is when an Acceptable Source Prefix becomes invalid
      (e.g., if the Border Router which announced it crashes, or
      its WAN link goes down). In this case, current hosts will continue
      to use source addresses in that Acceptable Source Prefix without
      knowing that all communication outside the network is likely to
      fail. In this case, interior routers can improve responsiveness
      by deprecating the addresses in that Acceptable Source Prefix.
      </t>

      <t>ICMP <xref target="RFC4443"/> includes a Destination
      unreachable code 5 - "Source address failed ingress/egress
      policy". Hosts MUST adhered to this message, and based on the
      unreachable message try another source address.</t>
    </section>

    <!--  SECTION 4:  IANA Considerations           -->

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This specification does not require any IANA actions.</t>
    </section>

    <!--  SECTION 5:  Security Considerations      	-->

    <section title="Security Considerations">
    </section>

    <!--  SECTION 6:  Contributors     			-->


    <!--  SECTION 7:  Acknowledgements     			-->

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Jari Arkko and Andrew
      Yourtchenko for their ideas and review.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <!--  SECTION 8.1:  Normative References		-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      &I-D.arkko-homenet-prefix-assignment;
      &I-D.ietf-ospf-ospfv3-autoconfig;
      &RFC2827;
      &RFC5340;
      &RFC6724;
      &RFC4443;
    </references>

    <!--  SECTION 8.2:  Informative References		-->

    <references title="Informative References">
      &I-D.ietf-homenet-arch;
      &I-D.baker-ipv6-ospf-dst-src-routing;
      &I-D.baker-ipv6-isis-dst-src-routing;
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
